[{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these statements about succession is incorrect?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Succession is a change of species composition, community structure and function over time and space","Succession is usually set in motion by some sort of disturbance","Succession is both directional and predictable","Succession begins only on a bare ground"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Example of genetic diseases include any of the following except ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["diabetes","cystic fibrosis","hepatitis","epilepsy"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In his theory of evolution, Darwin identified ... as the main cause of natural selection<\/strong><\/p>","options":["physiological pressure","ecological pressure","environmental pressure","biological pressure"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these is not a unique feature of meiosis<\/strong><\/p>","options":["synapsis","homologous recombination","reduction division","cytokinesis"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these organisms is not an autotroph<\/strong><\/p>","options":["spirogyra","zea may","rhizobium","mushroom"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these feature is not typical of most animals<\/strong><\/p>","options":["heterotrophic","multicellular","sessile","motile at some stage of life cycle"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The cnidarians use their nematocysts only for ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["capturing prey","courtship","gas exchange","sensing chemicals"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the following is not true<\/strong><\/p>","options":["saprophytic nutrition involves feeding on soluble organic material from inorganic substances","symbiosis is a nutritional relationship in which both organisms involved derive benefit","a parasite causes injuries to its host in the course of getting its food","holozoic mode of nutrition can be seen in animals, carnivorous plants and some protists"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In which biome would you expect to have the shortest growing season?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["tropical rain forest","guinea savanna","sudan savanna","desert"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The concept of tropic structure of a community emphasizes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the dominant form of vegetation","the main predator","the feeding relationship within a community","the richness of species in the community"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these is an agency responsible for conserving natural resources in Nigeria<\/strong><\/p>","options":["PDP","NCF","ACC","NEMA"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which happens to a tadpole after 45 days old?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["it becomes fully grown, mouth becomes wider, horny jaw disappears completely","it becomes fully grown, mouth becomes wider, tail disappears completely","it becomes fully grown, mouth becomes wider, external gill disappears completely","it becomes fully grown, mouth becomes wider, slit disappears partially"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a human skin cell with 46 chromosomes divide by mitosis, how many chromosomes will each daughter cell have?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["23","12","46","92"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Effect of air pollution does not include...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["formation of carboxyl hemoglobin","displacement of digested food","lowering plant yield","damage breathing organs"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The lack of special supportive structures in bryophtes restricts them to one of the following types of growth<\/strong><\/p>","options":["lateral growth","upward growth","downward growth","aerial growth"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Physical observable characteristics of an organism is called ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["genotype","phenotype","allele","locus"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the evolutionary trend, in which phylum do we begin to see a complete digestive track?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["ctenophora","platyhelminthes","nematoda","mollusca"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Absorption is maximum in the small intestine because of ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the presence of wili","its length","its thin walls","all of the above"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In man, abnormality with chromosome 21 often leads to a genetic problem called...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Respiratory syndrome","Carcinoma syndrome","Klinefelter","Down syndrome"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The presence of extensive amounts of rough endoplasmic reticulum in a cell is an indication that the cell is involved in ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["synthesis and metabolism of CH<sub>2<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","synthesis and secretion of proteins","synthesis of ATP","contraction"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not present in RNA?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Adenine","Guanine","Cytosine","Thymine"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of thses components of the phloem has the cytoplasm pushed to the sides while also lacking nucleus?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["companion cell","sieve tube elements","sieve plate","parenchyma"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements about phylum Cnidaria is correct?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["they are diploblastic animals","body is sac-shaped with three openings","they are bilaterally symmetrical","they are triploblastic animals with two openings"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these biological statement is correct?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["reflex actions are also known as involuntary actions","the fore brain consists of the cerebrum and the olfactory lobes","the right hemisphere of the brain controls the right half of the body","the outer part of the human cerebrum is made up of grey matter"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The best known plant species that occur in fresh swamp vegetation is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Rihzophora racemosa","Acrostichum aureum","Mitragyna ciliate","Triplochiton scleroxylon"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Bacteria that live in the human intestine assist in the digestion and feed on nutrients the body consumed. This relationship might best be described as...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Commensalism","Ectoparasitism","Endoparasitism","Mutualism"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The xylem elements perform the function of transport but they also help to support plants because they<\/strong><\/p>","options":["are internally located","are tubular","have rigid thick wall","constantly absorb water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Biosphere is best described as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["all parts of the earth where life exists","the non-living parts of an ecosystem","all component of an ecosystem","all the members of a single species in a habitat"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Muscle fatigue is caused by...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["accumulation of ethanol in the muscle cells","accumulation of methanol in the muscle cells","accumulation of lactic acid in the muscle cells","accumulation of pyruvic acid in the muscle"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>At what stage of the meiotic prophase do the homologous chromosomes attract each other and then pair up?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Leptotene","Paachytene","Zygotene","Diplotene"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the organelles is not directly connected to cell division process?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["centromere","microtubules","golgi bodies","spindle apparatus"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>During the light dependent reaction<\/strong><\/p>","options":["glucose is formed","carbon IV oxide is fixed","NADPH and ATP are synthesized using electron released from water","water is split and the electrons produced are used for glucose synthesis"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Meiosis II is similar to mitosis in that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["homologous chromosome synapse","sister chromatids during anaphase","the chromosome number is reduced","the daughter cells are diploid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The mechanism of opening and closing the stomata is associated with the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["guard cells","stoma","lenticels","air spaces"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Holozoic is seen in <\/strong><\/p>","options":["animals, carnivorous plants and protozoans","animals, protist and carnivorous plants","animals, carnivorous plants and fungi","animals, fungi and protist"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The part of the tooth that contains blood vessels and verve fibres is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["root","enamel","entine","pulp cavity"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The food substance that are stored in readiness for times of food shortages are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["carbohydrates","fats and oil","proteins","vitamins"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is the role of the liver in digestion?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["synthesis of lipase","secretion of trypsin","secretion of bile and bicarbonate for emulsification of fats","otorego of bile for hydrolyses of starch"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Respiratory surfaces generally have the following characteristics with exception of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["it must be thick but permeable","it must be moist","it must pass a large surface area","it must be richly supplied with blood vessels"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is not a water soluble vitamin?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["thiamine","riboflavin","folic acid","calciferol"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these following biomes is currently being ravaged by desertification?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["derived savanna","southern guinea savanna","northern guinea savanna","sudan savanna"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which is the largest of the middle ear ossicles?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["anvil","stripe","hammer","incus"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The process by which plants and animals are modified in structure, physiology and behaviour in order to survive is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["evolution","adaptation","succession","aggregation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these plants can withstand extreme dryness?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["cactus","raphia palm","triplochiton scleroxylon","parkia biglobosa"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Animals that do not allow their body temperature to vary with the ambient are called?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["homoeothermic","poikilothermic","amphibians","reptiles"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The number of cranial nerves that connect the brain to various parts of the body is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["10 pairs","11 pairs","12 pairs","13 pairs"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following pair of ions is involved in transmission of impulses by neutrons:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["K and N ions","Na and Mg ions","K and Cl ions","K and Ca ions"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The probability of producing an heterozygote progeny in a cross between two heterozygote individuals of pea plant is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1\/3","1\/4","1\/2","2\/3"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these does not protect the body from harmful effect of disease-causing micro-organisms<\/strong><\/p>","options":["anti toxin","phagocytes","antigens","antibodies"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these statements with respect to individual organism is most correct?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["it refers to animals only","it refers to either the plant or animal","its ecology can be carried out in zoo only","it is used in reference to plant only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these is not a major Biome in West Africa<\/strong><\/p>","options":["rain forest","savanna","cornferous forest","mangroove"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The media of transportation in living things include all but<\/strong><\/p>","options":["cytoplasm","water","eosin","blood and lymph"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Gaseous exchange through the lungs is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["cutaneous breathing","buccal breathing","pulmonary breathing","larynxial breathing"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>In saprophytic mode of nutrition<\/strong><\/p>","options":["organisms feed on insoluble organic material","decomposition is not possible at all","nutrient recycling is possible","no animal is involved"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>A macro element which is not directly connected with formation of chlorophyll is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["nitrogen","iron","magnesium","sulphur"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>During the light dependent reaction<\/strong><\/p>","options":["glucose is formed","carbon IV oxide is fixed","NADPH and ATP are synthesized using electron released from water","water is split and the electrons produced are used for glucose synthsis"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Eutrophication refers to growth of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["bacteria","fungi","protophytes","algae"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>All the following statements are consistent with the concept of trophic structure except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["at every feeding stage some energy is wasted from the chain","the nearer the organism to the beginning of the food chain, the greater the available energy of the organism","the first trophic level is occupied by the autotrophs","there are few number of organisms at the start of a food chain"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>All these statements about plants succession are correct except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["plant succession is the process of community change at one place over time","plant succession is usually measured over the course of several years to hundred years","succession proceeds from pioneer to climax phases","succession is often not directional and so difficult to predict"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not true about finger print?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["it is useful in detecting crime","no two individual have the same finger print","it is a heritable character","it is environmentally induced"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Characteristics of continuous variation include all the following except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["produced by many genes","influenced by the environment","occurs in a normal distribution curve","most of the organisms in the population fall at the tail ends of the range"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Homeostasis is defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["regulation of both external and internal conditions of organisms","maintenance of internal environment of an organism","maintenance of internal and external environment of an organism","regulation of the chemical environment of an organism"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Effectors are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["muscles which work in response to the stimulus received from the motor nerves","glands which work in response to the stimulus received from the motor nerves","muscles or glands which work in response to the stimulus received from the motor nerves","efferent neutrons"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The mechanism of opening and closing stomata is associated with the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["guard cells","stoma","lenticels","air spaces"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The part of the kidney where each tubule begins is called&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["capsule","cortex","glomerulus","urether"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>The factors for two pairs of contrasting characters are inherited independent of each other. This is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Menders first law of inheritance","Mendel's second law of inheritance","Mendel's law of segregation of germinal units","Mendel's law of independent pairing of germinal units"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>All of the following green algae are colonial forms except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["gonium","volvox","pandorina","anabaena"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Allele is <\/strong><\/p>","options":["an alternate form of a gene","a unit of inheritance","the position or location of the gene on a chromosome","number of chromosomes in the gamete"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these statements about sympathetic Nervous system is untrue<\/strong><\/p>","options":["it stimulates many parts of the body in times of danger","it stimulates the heart beat","it functions like the adrenal glands","it lowers the blood pressure"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the following elements is not associated with leaf chlorosis<\/strong><\/p>","options":["nitrogen","iron","calcium","magnesium"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"<p><strong>Hierarchical organization of living organism is in one of the following orders<\/strong><\/p>","options":["atoms, molecules, compound, cells, tissues, organs, systems, organism","atoms, molecules, organelles, cells, tissues, organs, systems, organism","atoms, elements, molecules, cells, tissues, organs, systems, organism","atoms, molecules, elements, cells, tissues, organs, organ systems, organism"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Steepness of slope generally affect ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["rainfall","drainage","sunlight","all of the options"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Bacteria differ from eukaryotic forms of life in that they:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["are causes of all infectious disease","have no nuclear membrane","reproduce by binary fission","have a thick cell-wall"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements is NOT correct? Hormones<\/strong><\/p>","options":["are circulated by blood and lymph","have their effect on target organs","complement nervous co-ordination","are not produced in specific glands"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Sister chromalids are:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["two identical copies of a single chromosome produced during s-phase","pairs of chromosomes","points of attachments of centromeres to the chromosomes","chromosomes found in cells of sisters"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the groups of organism below is critial in the entire process of nutrient cycling<\/strong><\/p>","options":["aves","nematode","mammalian","fungi"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>If 80 grasshoppers are found in a field with a total area of 100cm<sup>2<\/sup>, what is the population density of grasshopper in the field?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.08 per m<sup>2<\/sup>","0.8m<sup>2<\/sup>","80m<sup>2<\/sup>","100m<sup>2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is part of the axial skeleton in a mammal?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["phalange","tarsal","sacrum","patella"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major difference between Arachnids and Annelids is that ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["in annelids, body consists of dissimilar segments unlike in arachnids","in annelids, body consists of similar segments unlike in arachnids","in annelids, the cephalothoraxas is not distinct unlike in arachnids","in annelids, the cephalothoraxas is distinct unlike in arachnids"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The process in which the internal environment of an organism is maintained is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["co-ordination","homeostasis","excretion","metabolism"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the following organism exhibits a closed and single circulatory system<\/strong><\/p>","options":["insect","earthworm","fishes","mammals"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Coelomates are animals with&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["no body cavity","true body cavity","false body cavity","two germ layers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>This tissue is made up of tracheids, vessels, fibres and parenchyma. What is it?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["phloem","scelerenchyma","xylem","ground tissue"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The important processes which bring about recycling of carbon dioxide between the biotic and abiotic components of an ecosystem are all of the following except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["photosynthesis","respiration","decay","burning of fossil fuels"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>When a cut is made on the trunks of certain trees, the milky fluid excuded is called&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["rubber","resin","alkaloid","latex"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The type of farming which involves raising livestock only is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["mixed farming","subsistence farming","pastoral farming","monoculture"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Fruits that develop without fertilization are known as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["parthenocarpic fruits","aggregate fruits","simple fruits","epicarpic fruits"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Nerve endings are located in which part of the tooth?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["crown","cement","pulp cavity","gum"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is the hardest material in the body of animals?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["cartilagve","bone","enamel","dentine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Grasping fingers and toes as well as eyes positioned in front of the head are features of <\/strong><\/p>","options":["cartaceans","carnivores","rodents","primates"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the major difference between DNA and RNA is that ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["DNA is made of ribose sugar and double stranded unlike RNA","DNA is made of ribose sugar and single stranded unlike RNA","RNA is made of ribose sugar and double stranded unlike DNA","RNA is made of ribose sugar and single stranded unlike DNA"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these statement is true of caryopsis<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pericarp and seed coat are fused","pericarp is free from seed coat","pericarp splits open","pericarp with a superior ovary"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A biological species must possess the following characteristics except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["live only in one place","must interbreed","must produce fertile offspring","the mating between members must be free"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these groups of animals rivals mammals in the display of parental care features?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["birds","reptiles","pisces","none of the above"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>An assemblage of populations of different species which interact through trophic and spatial relationship is best described as a(an)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["city","community","ecosystem","niche"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>In which biome would you expect to have the shortest growing season?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["tropical rain forest","guinea savanna","sudan savanna","deserts"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is an incorrect statement about savanna?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["it occupies about 80% of the land surface of Nigeria","it has no woody species","it is usually burnt annually","it is a closed or nearly closed cover of grasses"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following habitats cannot be used for the study of succession?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["abandoned farmland","a pond","savanna grassland","well cultivated farmland"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>In which of these associations is much harm done to one of the partners?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["symbiosis","commensalism","parasitism","mutualism"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Effect of air pollutant does not include:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["formation of carboxyl hemoglobin","displacement of digested food","lowering plant yield","damage breathing organs"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A typical feature of a plant cell is the presence of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["chromosome in nucleus","cellulose cell wall","mitochondria","membrane around the nucleus"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Non seed plants are found in&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["desert and arctic regions only","all environments","cold mountain areas and hot springs","tropical and subtropical regions only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following phyla has been found to be the most successful in the animal kingdom?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["phylum Annelida","phylum Arthropoda","phylum Chordata","phylum Mollusca"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Adaptive features of plants to desert conditions include<\/strong><\/p>","options":["thick barks, succulent stems and sunken stomata","thin barks, succulent stems and sunken stomata","thin barks, air floats on stems and sunken stomata","air spaces on tissues, adventitious roots and thin barks"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The distribution of plants in rainforest is governed mainly by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["vegetation","soil types","amount of rainfall","rainfall pattern"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The greatest influence on a stable ecosystem in nature is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["man","pollution","animal","rainfall"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is the basic unit of classification?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["genus","species","phylum","kingdom"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which two structures are present in a palisade cell but not in a liver?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["cell wall and cytoplasm","cell wall and chloroplast","cell membrane and cytoplasm","cell membrane and chloroplast"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Workers in deep mines usually suffer from dehydration because<\/strong><\/p>","options":["water is lost due to evaporation","water is lost due to defecation","water is lost in the form of sweat","water is lost along with salts in the form of sweat"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Glucose is reabsorbed in the kidney mainly by&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Bowman's capsule","Loop of Henle","Proximal convoluted tubule","distal convoluted tubule"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most common substrate of respiration is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["fats","amino acids","glucose","sucrose"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The rate of heart beat in an adult human being is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["71 beats per minute","72 beats per minute","73 beats per minute","74 beats per minute"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the following is not true<\/strong><\/p>","options":["saprophytic nutrition involves feeding on soluble organic material from inorganic substances","symbiosis is a nutritional relationship in which both organism involved drive benefit","a parasite causes injuries to its host in the course of getting its food","holozoic mode of nutrition can be seen in animals, carnivorous plants and some protists"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>... is responsible for the direction of growth and development of an organism<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the nucleus","DNA","the neuron","the RNA"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The chromosome number in man is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["46","23","92","58"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Effectors are&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["muscles which work in response to the stimulus received from the motor nerves","glands which work in response to the stimulus received from the motor nerves","muscles or glands which work in response to the stimulus received from the motor nerves","efferent neurons"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following are formed in the bone marrow except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["platelets","basophilis","granulocytes","lymphocytes"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is the basic unit of classification of plants and animals?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["genus","species","phylum","kingdom"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>An organism with a pair of indistinguishable genes is a <\/strong><\/p>","options":["heterozygote","hybrid","allelomorph","homozygote"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The fruit formed from a single flower having several carpels is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["multiple fruit","simple fruit","aggregate fruit","indehiscent fruit"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The functions of ossicles (malcus, incur and stapes) in the mammalian ear is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["vibrate","regulate pressures","support of the inner ear","maintain balance during motion"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Joint skeleton is absent in the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["cockroach","spider","millipede","snail"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Mucors and spirogyra can be put in the same group because they<\/strong><\/p>","options":["have spors are dispersed by wind","unicellular","reproduce sexually","have bodies made up of thallus and filame alternatively"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The organ through which nourishment and oxygen diffuse into an embryo is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["amnion","chorion","unbilical cord","placenta"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong> A tapeworm fasten itself to the intestine of its host with<\/strong><\/p>","options":["neck & bicker","hooks & suckers","rostellum & suckers","rostellum, hooks and suckers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is false about the piliferous layer of a root?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["has a thin cuticle","is outermost layer of the cortex","may bear root hairs","breaks down with age"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Anaerobic respiration in yeast produce<\/strong><\/p>","options":["CO<sub>2<\/sub> and ethanol","CO<sub>2<\/sub> and H<sub>2<\/sub>O","CO<sub>2<\/sub> and O<sub>2<\/sub>","CO<sub>2<\/sub> and glucose"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which one of these set of factors is completely abiotic?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["turbidity, tide, salinity, plankton","pressure, pH, soil, insect","water, soil, bacteria, salinity","light, altitude, wind, humidity"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>In which of these are flagella and cilia found<\/strong><\/p>","options":["flatworms","protozoa","elenterates","annelids"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The three important organs that are situated close to the stomach are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["liver, kidney and gall bladder","pancreas, liver and kidney","gall bladder, pancreas and spleen","liver, kidney and spleen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The plantain reproduces sexually by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["spores","buds","sucker","flowers"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The major functions of swim-bladder in fish is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["breathing","swimming","repelling enemy","buoyancy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The part of the central nervous system concerned with answering and examination question is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["cerebellum","orxy","cerebrum","medullar oblangata"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Wind pollinated flowers usually have<\/strong><\/p>","options":["long style","sticky stigma","small and short stigma","short styles and pollen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The radicle of a bean seedling grows mostly rapidly in the region<\/strong><\/p>","options":["of the root tip","below the topsoil","just round the root tip","just below the root tip"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A key to similarity between nervous and hormonal system is that both<\/strong><\/p>","options":["involve chemical transmission","have widespread effects","shed chemicals into the blood stream","eliminate response"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The bones of the neck on which the skull rest is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["odontoid","axis","occipital","atlas"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A child with blood group genotype different from those of both parents and with a mother of genotype OO, can only have a father of genotype A...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A","B","OO","AB"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A true climax commuity<\/strong><\/p>","options":["changes from year to year","persists until the environment change","is the first stage in plant succession","consists of tallest trees and small animals"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a predator food chain involving secondary and tertiary consumers, the organisms become progressively<\/strong><\/p>","options":["smaller","equal in number","larger and fewer along the food chain","sparse in distribution"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is false about the piliferous layer of a root?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["has a thin cuticle","is outermost layer of the cortex","may bear root hairs","breaks down with age"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>When it is cold the blood vessels of the skin<\/strong><\/p>","options":["dilate to increase blood flow","constrict to reduce the amount of flow of blood","dilate to reduce the amount of blood flow to the skin","constrict to increase the amount of blood flowing to the skin"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"}]